Guide to the Collection of John Bachmann Prints 1849-1885 PR 353
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Collection of John Bachmann Prints
1849-1885
PR 353
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
3.0 Linear feet (3 folders)
This collection consists of 23 bird's-eye view lithographic prints created by Swiss-born American artist John Bachmann (1814-1896). The prints date from 1849 to circa 1885.
Bachmann, John, active 1849-1885
Arrangement Note
The prints are arranged in two series. Thereunder they are filed chronologically.
Series I. Views of New York City
Series II. Views of Other Cities
Biographical/Historical Note
John Bachmann (1814–1896) was a German-speaking Swiss printmaker and artist best known for his bird's-eye views, especially of New York City. Bachmann was a journeyman lithographer in Switzerland and Paris until 1847. His first known American print appeared in 1849; it is a view from an imagined point above Union Square in New York, looking south toward the Battery. This print is credited to "C. Bachman" as artist and "J. Bachmann" as publisher; his name appears on subsequent prints as both Bachman and Bachmann.
In 1850-1851, he published a series of bird's-eye views of American cities, including Boston, New York, Philadelphia, New Orleans and Washington, D.C. Bachmann married in about 1852, and had four children, the eldest of whom became a lithographer. Around 1860, the family moved to Hoboken NJ, and in 1864 settled in Jersey City Heights, NJ. Bachmann continued producing prints, the majority of which were views of New York and Central Park, until about 1885. Bachmann's prints were among the first major bird's eye views, as opposed to panoramic views, in the United States. Although they appear to be captured from above, bird's eye views were actually mathematically compiled on a grid using hundreds of sketches done on the ground. Bachmann's skillful use of the bird's-eye view helped popularize it as a way of portraying modern urban geography, and launched a new genre of American printmaking.
Sources: Case, Nat. "John Bachmann and the American Bird's Eye View Print", Imprint, Vol. 33, Number II, Autumn 2008, pp.19-35.
Reps, John W. Views and Viewmakers of Urban America. (Columbia, MO: University of Missouri Press, 1984.)
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
This collection has been compiled from a variety of gifts and purchases. View of Central Park, New York City (circa 1875) was purchased January 2018. The other prints were previously part of the Geographic File PR 20.
Related Archival Materials Note
Additional printed views of New York City can be found in the Geographic File PR 20, the Boyd Collection PR 07, and the Printmaker File PR 58. All bound volumes of New York City and other views arecatalogued in the Library’s catalog, BOBCAT.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection consists of 23 bird's-eye view lithographic prints created by artist John Bachmann (1814-1896). The prints date from 1849 to circa 1885. Eighteen of the prints are views of New York City; the remaining five are of other cities, including Boston, Hoboken, New Orleans, Philadelphia, and Washington, DC.
Aerial views; Bird's-eye view prints; Bird's-eye views; Boston (Mass.)--Aerial views.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.)--Aerial views.; Central Park (New York, N.Y.)--Aerial views.; Hoboken (N.J.)--Aerial views.; Lithographs; New Orleans (La.)--Aerial views.; New York (N.Y.)--Aerial views; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Aerial views; Washington (D.C.)--Aerial views.
- Series I: Views of New York, 1849-circa 1885
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series consists of 18 bird's-eye view lithographs of New York City, arranged chronologically.
  - New-York, 1849 (Folder FF1)
    View south from Union Square. J. Bachmann, artist. Sarony & Major, lithographers. Published by John Bachmann, 5 Rector Street, New York.
  - New York City Hall, Park and Environs, circa 1850 (Folder FF1)
    Copy 1. Bachmann, artist and lithographer. Published by Williams and Stevens, 353 Broadway, New York.
  - New York City Hall, Park and Environs, circa 1850 (Folder FF1)
    Copy 2. Bachmann, artist and lithographer. Published by Williams and Stevens, 353 Broadway, New York.
  - Birds Eye View of New York and Brooklyn, 1850 (Folder FF1)
    J. Bachmann, artist and printer. Published by John Bachmann, 218 William Street, NY.
  - Birds Eye View of the New York Crystal Palace and Environs, 1853 (Folder FF1)
    J. Bachmann, artist. Published by John Bachmann, 37 City Hall Place, NY.
  - Brooklyn. Bird's Eye View of the City of New York. Williamsburg., 1859 (Folder FF1)
    J. Bachmann, artist. Published by C. Magnus & Co.
  - New-York and Environs, 1861 (Folder FF1)
    Round shape, fisheye view. J. Bachmann, artist. Published by J. Bachmann, 115 Nassau Street, New York.
  - Central Park, 1863 (Folder FF1)
    Bird's eye view with a series of smaller vignettes around the border. John Bachmann, artist. Printed by F. Heppenheimer. Published by John Bachmann, 76 Nassau Street, New York.
  - Birds Eye View of the Central Park, New-York, 1865 (Folder FF2)
    Copy 1. J. Bachmann, artist. J. Bien, lithographer. Published by Bachmann.
  - Birds Eye View of the Central Park, New York, 1865 (Folder FF2)
    Copy 2. J. Bachmann, artist. J. Bien, lithographer. Published by Bachmann.
  - Central Park [Summer], 1865 (Folder FF2)
    J. Bachmann, artist. J. Bien, lithographer. Published by Edmund Foerster & Co.
  - Central Park [Winter], [1865] (Folder FF2)
    J. Bachmann, artist. J. Bien, lithographer. Published by Edward Fuerster.
  - Birds Eye View of New York and Environs, 1865 (Folder FF2)
    J. Bachmann, artist. J. Bien, printer. Published by John Bachmann, 76 Nassau Street, New York.
  - View of Central Park, New York, [1875] (Folder FF2)
    View looking southeast. John Bachmann, artist. H. Bencke, lithographer.
  - View of New York, 1877 (Folder FF2)
    View of Manhattan from the southeast, with Statue of Liberty visible in NY harbor. J. Bachmann, artist. H. Bencke, lithographer.
  - View of New York and Vicinity, 1879 (Folder FF2)
    View north from New York harbor. John Bachmann, artist. H. Bencke, lithographer.
  - Bird's Eye View Of Coney Island. Bird's Eye View of Rockaway., [circa 1881] (Folder FF2)
    Two views on one sheet. Copyright by John Bachmann, 80 Bower Street Jersey City Heights
  - View of New York, [circa 1885] (Folder FF2)
    View from the southwest, showing Manhattan and Brooklyn. J. Bachmann, artist. Snyder and Black, printers. Published by J. Bachmann, 80 Bower Street, Jersey City Heights.
- Series II: Views of Other Cities, 1850-1874
  This series consists of 5 bird's-eye view lithographs of American cities outside of New York, arranged chronologically.
  - Bird's Eye View of Boston, 1850 (Folder FF3)
    J. Bachmann, artist. Sarony & Major, lithographer. Williams and Stevens, publisher.
  - Birds Eye View of Philadelphia, 1850 (Folder FF3)
    J. Bachmann, artist. Sarony & Major, lithographers. Williams and Stevens, publisher.
  - Bird's Eye View of New Orleans, 1851 (Folder FF3)
    J. Bachmann, artist and printer. A. Guerber & Co., publisher.
  - Birds-Eye View of Washington, D.C. and Environs, 1865 (Folder FF3)
    J. Bachmann, artist. Printed and published by Kimmel & Forster, 254-256 Canal Street, New York
  - Hoboken, 1874 (Folder FF3)
    J. Bachmann, artist. Published by F. Luthin, 197 Washington Street Hoboken, New Jersey